Guide to the Records of United for Peace and Justice TAM.513
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United For Peace and Justice Records
circa 1980-2009
2002-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
United for Peace and Justice
Kielson, Leslie R.
TAM.513
14 Linear Feet in 7 records cartons, 6 oversize flat boxes, 1 oversize object box, and three oversized folders
The United for Peace and Justice (UFPJ) is an anti-war coalition organization that organizes opposition to U.S. military involvement in Iraq and Afghanistan, against nuclear weapons, and for economic and social justice. The collection contains minutes and other materials from steering committee and national assembly meetings, internal documents related to the planning of demonstrations and other activities, and publicity materials for these activities. In addition to the printed material, there are photographs and artifacts including picket signs, political buttons, posters, banners, t-shirts, a box of audiocassetttes, and one videocassette.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Leslie R. Kielson on behalf of United for Peace and Justice in 2009. The accession number associated with this collection is 2009.062.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist, other than some preliminary moving of photographs, banners, and picket signs into containers separate from paper text records.
Historical/Biographical Note
United For Peace and Justice (UFPJ) was founded in 2002 in Washington DC, and began as a national campaign to bring together a broad range of organizations throughout the United States to help coordinate work against a U.S. war on Iraq. Its first major rally took place on February 15, 2003, global day of protest, called The World Says No to War. UFPJ helped coordinate and publicize more than 790 demonstrations worldwide. Two days after the bombing of Iraq began, on March 22, 2003, UFPJ mobilized more than 300,000 people for a protest march down Broadway in New York City, which in successive years would be a major protest day for the UFPJ. Its first National Assembly took place in June of 2003, coordinating actions against President George W. Bush's war policies and solidifying UFPJ's organizational structure. The Assembly met again in 2005, 2007, and 2009, organizing its anti-war and other campaigns.
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the records of United for Peace and Justice, as well as some records of its New York City Chapter, including subject/activities files and administrative materials related to rallies, demonstrations, and campaigns sponsored by the organization, the majority of which were in opposition to U.S. wars in the Middle East, or in opposition to nuclear weapons. Materials included are minutes, agendas, National Assembly meeting packets, clippings, fliers, leaflets, other printed ephemera, and reports, including proposals for future campaigns. In addition, there are photographs and artifacts that include picket signs, political buttons, posters, banners, and t-shirts. Audio materials comprise one box of audiocassetttes, containing talks on various topics, several Herbert Aptheker study series tapes, recordings of Pacifica National/WBAI programs, "Paint the Town Red" Communist Party songs, a Jewish Affairs dinner, and unlabeled tapes. Materials also include one videocassette, "The Bomb in Boston Teach-In," June 25, 1983.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Political posters, American.; Buttons (information artifacts).; Photographs.; Picket signs.; Social justice -- United States.; Minutes (administrative records); Printed ephemera.; Reports.; Peace movements -- United States.; Afghan War, 2001 -- Protest movements -- United States; Fliers (printed matter); Iraq War, 2003-2011 -- Protest movements -- United States.; Banners.; Kielson, Leslie R.
- Records, 2002-2005 (Box 1)
  Scope and Content Note
  Contains files on rallies hosted by UFPJ, including the "Turn Your Back on Bush" anti-war rally and march on Inauguration Day, January 20, 2005 and "Abolition Now! No Nukes! No War!" rally on May 1, 2005, notes from its 2004 planning conference, a clippings file on Central Park events, and other activities. The files include minutes, memos, contact and phone lists, fliers, press releases, and brochures and postcards.
- Records, 2005-2008 (Box 2)
  Contains the files from events paraticipated in and/or hosted by UFPJ including its 2nd National Assembly in 2005, the Peace and Justice Festival in Washington DC, September 24-26, 2005, the Foley Square Festival on April 29, 2006, March on Washington in January of 2007, the US Social Forum in 2007, the No More Foreign Bases campaign in 2007, March 20, 2008 rally marking the 5th anniversary of the Iraq War, the Global Network Against Weapons and Nuclear Power in Space Conference in April 2008, protests planned around the 2008 Republican National Convention, and the Cleveland Conference National Assembly to End the Iraq War and Occupation, June 2008. The files contain minutes, ballots for steering committee elections, budgets, event evaluations, fliers, memos, leaflets, logistics, press releases, proposals for campaigns to be undertaken, and and other documents.
- Records, 2003-2009 (Box 3)
  Contains files on events participated in or organized by the UFPJ, including the protest at the Republican National Convention in 2004, the March 19th, 2005 anti-war rally on the anniversary of the beginning of the Iraq War, the No Nukes! No Wars! protest with Abolition Now in 2005, an antiwar March on Washington on September 24, 2005, and the Iraqi Labor speaking Tour in 2005. The box contains planning material for these events, including agendas, fliers, internal correspondence, logistics, press kits, sign-in sheets, and program notes. This box also steering committee meeting minutes and National Assembly meetings packets.
- Records, 2003-2009 (Box 4)
  Contains files from the First National Assembly in 2003 and the Second National Assembly in 2005. The files include registration and participant lists, nomination forms for the steering committee, recommendations for travel scholarships, steering committee local/regional ballots, proposals for future campaigns, packets, member group lists, participant feedback forms, stategic framework, memos, and budgets. This box also contains some materials from the fourth National Assembly in 2009, including packets. Other files included are on campaign planning, clippings on demonstrations, and an action plan for the UFPJ. The box also contains event notices from many different UFPJ sponsored events, including fliers and circulars. The box also holds some articles and the UFPJ's leaflets on demonstrations or campaigns that UFPJ supported.
- Records, 2003-2009 (Box 5)
  Contains files from events and campaigns participated in and/or hosted by the UFPJ including a silent vigil on September 11, 2003, Stop the War program on February 15, 2003, Occupation Watch Center in Baghdad funding in 2003, the National Campaign for non-violent resisting in 2004, the Counter Recruitment campaign in 2004, Operation Ceasefire support concert in 2005, the Witness against Torture Campaign (Shut Down Gitmo campaign) in 2006, NYC Peace Zone Campaign in 2006, Million Doors for Peace campaign in 2008, and their Third National Assembly in 2007 and their Fourth National Assembly in 2009. The files contain agendas, amendments to proposals for upcoming campaigns, breakout group notes, participant evaluations, floor plans, follow-up notes, memos, minutes, circulars, participant packet, planning materials, ranking of priorities ballots, steering committee nominations and ballots, venue payments, and other records. Other records included are legal materials from the New York Civil Liberties Union lawsuit against NYPD practices in anticipation of the Republican National Convention in 2004, FOIA papers from the FBI, clippings about the FBI admitting to monitoring groups including UFPJ from 2004-2006, an open letter of complaint by some member organizations to UFPJ in 2005, NYC UFPJ branch records, including, minutes, reports, Iraq War fact sheets, and fliers. National UFPJ materials include agendas, budgets, minutes, notes, news, participant lists, planning, and proposals from steering committee meetings, from July 2003 to January 2009.
- Records, 2003-2009 (Box 6)
  Contains files of the UFPJ steering committee meetings from July 2006 to January 2009, including minutes and reports, fundraising and planning materials. Also contains files from events, campaigns, and rallies hosted by the UFPJ, including the June 23, 2003 anti-George W. Bush demonstration, the October 25, 2003 anti-occupation rally, the anti-war rally on March 20, 2004, Democratic National Convention rallies in 2004 in Boston, rallies during the Republican National Convention (RNC) in 2004 in New York City, the Defend the Right to Free Assembly campaign and the conflict with Parks Department for permits to protest in 2004, the Turn Up the Heat Action Plan in 2004, the June 4, 2005 Northeast Peace and Justice Action Conference at Sage College in Albany, and the March on Wasington in September 2005. These records include leaflets, logistics, planning materials, phonebanking instructions, permits, posters, press notices, sales plans, use authorizations, and other material related to the events and campaigns.
- Records, 1983-1996 (Box 7)
  This box contains one video tape, "The Bomb in Boston Teach-In," June 25, 1983 and audio cassettes on black feminism, several Herbert Aptheker study series tapes, Pacifica National/WBAI program tapes, Paint the Town Red Communist party songs, Witnesses to the Holocaust audiocassette, a Jewish Affairs dinner, and unlabeled tapes.
- Photographs, t-shirts, sweatshirt, political buttons, cloth banners, bumper sticker, framed certificate of appreciation, circa 2002-2009 (Box 8)
- Picket signs, posters, and mounted front pages of newspapers, circa 2002-2009 (Box 9)
- Plastic banners, Circa 2003 (Box 10)
  General
  Four rolled blue banners, 24 inches wide by 10 feet long when unrolled.
- Plastic banners, Circa 2003 (Box 11)
  Two red and two green rolled banners, 24 inches wide by 10 feet long when unrolled.
- Plastic banners, Circa 2003 (Box 12)
  Three black and one purple rolled banners, 24 inches x 10 feet when unrolled.
- Plastic banners, Circa 2003 (Box 13)
  Two orange rolled banners, 24 inches by 10 feet when unrolled; one yellow and one white banner, folded, larger than the orange banners when unfolded.
- Plastic banners - extra oversized, Circa 2003 (Box 14)
- Oversized picket signs, posters, and "assembly collage" (possibly an exhibit created for display at a conference), Circa 2002-2009 (Flat-file-folder 2, Flat-file-folder 3)
- Archived Website, Oct 1, 2007-ongoing
  United for Peace and Justice, founded in 2002, is a coalition of more than 1400 local and national groups that organizes opposition to U.S. military involvement in Iraq and Afghanistan, against nuclear weapons, and for economic and social justice. The website contains action alerts, news listings, event listings, and other resources.